[
  {
    "question": "In the context of eighteenth-century India, what was\nDastak?",
    "choices": "a) Signature\nb)Land document\nc) Trade Permit\nd) Tax on textiles",
    "answer": "(c) Trade Permit", 
 "topic": "British Conquest of India"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which\nMaratha\nstatesman signed the Treaty\nof Bassein\non\nDecember 31, 1802?",
    "choices": "a) Baji Rao II\nb) Vithuji Holkar\nc) Daulat Rao Sindhia\nd) Madhava Rao Narayan",
    "answer": "(a) Baji Rao II", 
 "topic": "British Conquest of India"
  },
  {
    "question": "Chronologically\narrange\nthe\nfollowing\ntreaties/conventions\nsigned between the Marathas and the British (starting with the\nearliest):\n1. Treaty of Salbai\n2. Treaty of Purandar\n3.Convention of Wadgaon\n4.Treaty of Surat\nSelect the correct answer using the code given below :\na)4-2-3-1\nb)4-3-2-1\nc) 1-3-2-4\nd)1-2-3-4",
    "choices": "a)4-2-3-1\nb)4-3-2-1\nc) 1-3-2-4\nd)1-2-3-4",
    "answer": "(a) 4-2-3-1", 
 "topic": "British Conquest of India"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which\none of the following statements about the Treaty of\nAllahabad is NOT correct?\na)lt was signed in the year 1765\nb) The Mughal Emperor by\na\nfarman, formally granted the\nDiwani\nof\nBengal,\nBihar\nand\nOrissa\nto\nthe\nEast\nIndia\nCompany\nC\nAwadh\nwas restored to its\nNawab\non payment of Rs.\n50\nLakhs\nd)Banaras and the Surrounding tracts\nwere detached from\nAwadh and handed over to Shah Alam",
    "choices": "a)lt was signed in the year 1765\nb) The Mughal Emperor by\na\nfarman, formally granted the\nDiwani\nof\nBengal,\nBihar\nand\nOrissa\nto\nthe\nEast\nIndia\nCompany\nC\nAwadh\nwas restored to its\nNawab\non payment of Rs.\n50\nLakhs\nd)Banaras and the Surrounding tracts\nwere detached from\nAwadh and handed over to Shah Alam",
    "answer": "(d) Banaras and the Surrounding tracts were detached\nfrom Awadh and handed over to Shah Alam II", 
 "topic": "British Conquest of India"
  },
  {
    "question": "Consider the following statements:\n1.In the Third Battle of Panipat, Ahmad Shah Abdali defeated\nIbrahim Lodi.\n2. Tipu Sultan was killed in the Third Anglo- Mysore War:\n3. Mir Jafar entered in\na\nconspiracy with the English for the\ndefeat of Nawab Siraj ud- Daulah in the Battle of Plassey:\nWhich of the statements given above is/are correct?\n(a)\n1, 2 and 3\n(b)\n3 only\n(c)\n2 and 3\n(d)\nNone",
    "choices": "(a)\n1, 2 and 3\n(b)\n3 only\n(c)\n2 and 3\n(d)\nNone",
    "answer": "(b) 3 only", 
 "topic": "British Conquest of India"
  },
  {
    "question": "Consider the following Princely states ofthe British rule in India\n1.Jhansi\n2.Sambalpur\n3.Satara\nThe correct chronological order in which they were annexed\nthe British is:\n(a)\n1-2-3\n(b)\n1-3-2.\n(c)\n3-2-1\n(d)\n3-1-2",
    "choices": "(a)\n1-2-3\n(b)\n1-3-2.\n(c)\n3-2-1\n(d)\n3-1-2",
    "answer": "(c) 3-2-1", 
 "topic": "British Conquest of India"
  },
  {
    "question": "The First Anglo-Maratha War was concluded\nwhich one of\nthe following?\na) The Treaty of Surat\nb) The Treaty of Purandar\nc) The Convention of Wadgaon\nd) The Treaty of Salbai",
    "choices": "a) The Treaty of Surat\nb) The Treaty of Purandar\nc) The Convention of Wadgaon\nd) The Treaty of Salbai",
    "answer": "(d) The Treaty of Salbai", 
 "topic": "British Conquest of India"
  },
  {
    "question": "\nThe ruler of which one of the following states\nwas removed\nfrom power by the British on the pretext of misgovernance?\n(a)\nAwadh\n(b)\nJhansi\n(c)\nFrench\n(d)\nSatara",
    "choices": "(a)\nAwadh\n(b)\nJhansi\n(c)\nFrench\n(d)\nSatara",
    "answer": "(a) Awadh", 
 "topic": "British Conquest of India"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following is the correct chronological order of the\nbattles fought in India in the 18th Century?\n(a)\nBattle of Wandiwash,\nBattle of Buxar; Battle of Ambur;\nBattle of Plassey\n(b)\nBattle of Ambur; Battle of Plassey, Battle of Wandiwash,\nBattle of Buxar\n(c)\nBattle of Wandiwash, Battle of Plassey Battle of Ambur;\nBattle of Buxar\n(d)\nBattle of Ambur;\nBattle of Buxar Battle of Wandiwash,\nBattle of Plassey",
    "choices": "(a)\nBattle of Wandiwash,\nBattle of Buxar; Battle of Ambur;\nBattle of Plassey\n(b)\nBattle of Ambur; Battle of Plassey, Battle of Wandiwash,\nBattle of Buxar\n(c)\nBattle of Wandiwash, Battle of Plassey Battle of Ambur;\nBattle of Buxar\n(d)\nBattle of Ambur;\nBattle of Buxar Battle of Wandiwash,\nBattle of Plassey",
    "answer": "(b)\nBattle\nof Ambur;\nBattle\nof Plassey,\nBattle\nOf\nWandiwash, Battle f Buxar", 
 "topic": "British Conquest of India"
  },
  {
    "question": "Consider the following statements:\n1. The\nbattle\nof\nBuxar provided\nthe\nfor the English\nto\nestablish their rule in India.\n2. The Treaty of Allahabad, concluded in 1765, enabled the\nBritish to establish their rule in Bengal:\nWhich of the statements given above is /are correct?\na) 1 only\n6)2 only\nc) Both 1 and 2\nd)Neither 1 nor 2",
    "choices": "a) 1 only\n6)2 only\nc) Both 1 and 2\nd)Neither 1 nor 2",
    "answer": "(c) Both 1 and 2", 
 "topic": "British Conquest of India"
  },
  {
    "question": "Consider\nthe\nfollowing\nstatements\nabout\nthe\nTreaty\nof\nAmritsar (1809):\n1. The Treaty fixed the Sutlej as the boundary between the\nPunjab and British India\n2. It was after this treaty that Maharaja Ranjit Singh was able\nto annex Jammu, Multan and Kashmir to his domains.\nWhich of the statements given above is/are correct?\na) 1 only\nb)2 only\nc) Both 1and 2\nd)Neither 1 nor 2",
    "choices": "a) 1 only\nb)2 only\nc) Both 1and 2\nd)Neither 1 nor 2",
    "answer": "(c) Both 1 and 2", 
 "topic": "British Conquest of India"
  }
]